Let's talk for a moment about one of the most foundational aspects of how we come to the world,
and that is self-compassion. When we are compassionate with ourselves, we are more likely
to be healthy and whole. Where does self-compassion come from? And why is it so important?
I want to share some of the work of John Bolby, whose beautiful theory of the secure base
really informs our understanding of why and how self-compassion works.
We've all seen this beautiful scene unfold in front of us, which is a child in a restaurant
who decides that they want to go and explore. So they get off the chair and they run away
from their parents or caregivers, and then they do something so sweet. They turn to look back.
They are looking back to make sure that the parents or caregivers are still there.
The knowledge that if something goes wrong, the parents or caregivers will be able to step in,
then enables the child to even take more steps forward gleefully as they run away,
because this at its core is the essence of what the secure base is. The secure base is the
knowledge that if something goes wrong, I will be supported. And that in turn enables the child
to do all the things that a child needs to do, to learn, to grow, to take risks and to explore.
Now, if we think about this idea, this is what we are doing when we engage in self-compassion.
We are saying to ourselves, I have my own back. If something goes wrong, I will be there for me.
And it's the knowledge, the essence of this, that you've got your own back, that in turn
allows you to explore, to grow, and to take risks. Self-compassion is crucial, as we find our way forward
in a capacity that feels healthy and whole in our lives.